Frederick McEvoy Collection, 1956-1979 LCP2008/004
Liberian Collections
Frederick Dean McEvoy Collection,
1956-1979
Liberian Collections
McEvoy, Frederick Dean
LCP2008/004
2 cubic feet; 2 records cartons
The collection consists of field notes, research material, manuscripts and conference papers. Also included is a list of conference dates and papers that coincide. There is also a removed material Bibliography.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions for this collection.
Accession Information
Closed for research.
Biographical Note
Frederick Dean McEvoy was born on December 17, 1935, to Jesse and Reita Smith McEvoy in North Platte, Nebraska. McEvoy gained his initial experience in archaeology in 1951, as a summer assistant on an archaeological dig in North Dakota, under the direction of Dr. Richard P. Wheeler. Upon graduation from North Platte High School in 1953, he entered the University of Nebraska, Lincoln, completing one year of course work as an anthropology major. McEvoy subsequently joined the U.S. Navy and was trained as an air traffic controller; he served in the Philippines from 1958 to 1961. He married Hilda Seitz McEvoy in 1957; the couple had two daughters, Karen and Gwen. After discharge from the Navy in 1961, McEvoy returned to the University of Nebraska, studying anthropology, with a focus on the Omaha Indians. Following graduation in 1964, he received a Woodrow Wilson Foundation Fellowship for graduate study in anthropology at the University of Oregon. Studying under Dr. Vernon Dorjahn, McEvoy was awarded a National Science Foundation Fellowship for field research in Liberia from 1967-1968. Upon completion of his Ph.D. at University of Oregon, McEvoy taught anthropology at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, and subsequently at Marshall University in Huntington, West Virginia. While at Marshall University, McEvoy was also co-editor, along with Dr. Svend Holsoe, of volume 6 and 7 of the Liberian Studies Journal ( 1975-1977 ).
McEvoy left academia in 1979, moved to Denver, and initially worked for the non-profit organization, Denver Opportunity. From 1981 to 1989, he served as the Director of Research and Education at the Colorado State Civil Rights Division. In the mid-1990s, McEvoy worked for the West Virginia Division of Culture and History in Charleston. McEvoy relocated to his hometown of North Platte, Nebraska, in 2002; he passed away on April 1, 2007.
Arrangement
There are two main series Publications and Manuscripts and Field Notes and Research Material. Within the Publications and Manuscripts series there are two sub series "McEvoy" and "Other." Within the Field Notes and Research Material there are three sub series, "Field Notes," "Research Material," and "Liberian Research Binders." Liberian Research Binders are a sub series of their own due to their overlapping of both field and research material and the large number of binders in collection. Due to a large amount of overlapping material Field Notes and Research Material is the largest of the two series. All folders are listed chronologically, unless titled undated, which were then listed alphabetically at end of series.
Scope and Content
The collection consists mostly of field notes and research material describing McEvoy's time in Africa, primarily the Sabo region and the Firestone rubber plantations. Within the research and field material are maps, tables, charts. These usually consist of information on Migrant workers in the Sabo region. The collection also includes various manuscripts and conference papers written by McEvoy himself and other authors. Also included is a list of conference dates and papers that coincide as well as a removed material bibliography. Further more, it will be mentioned that the folder listed "Field Note Journals" are the raw material from which more understandable and typed field notes would come.
Papers by Conference
Below is a list of conferences and papers from those conferences. The papers are listed in a alphabetical order by the paper's title.
Eleventh Annual Meeting of the African Studies Association- Los Angeles, California, October 16-19 1968
Port Hardcourt: IBO Politics in Microcosm by Howard E. Wolpe
Research on the Uses of Kinship in Sabo Labor Migration by Frederick McEvoy
American Anthropological Association- Seattle, Washington, November 22, 1968
Kinship Obligations and Entrepreneurship: Conflicting or Supplementary? by Frederick McEvoy
Society for Applied Anthropology- Mexico City April 10 1969
Culture and Family Planning by Steven Polgar
Conference on Social Science Research in Liberia- Stanford University, August 1-2 1969
Some Problems in Sabo Kinship and Community Organization by Frederick McEvoy
Liberian Research Conference - 1970
What Liberians Call Themselves and Each Other by Svend Holsoe
Third Annual Conference on Liberian Social Science Research - University of Delaware 1971
Tubman and Liberia: The Grandeur and Potential Crisis of Charismatic Leadership by Losay A. Lalugba
15th Annual Meetings Northeastern Anthropological Association- Potsdam, New York April 16-19 1975
The Lack of Kpelle Entrepreneurs in Liberia: Current Trends and Prospects for the Future of Kpelle Society by Gerald M. Erchak
Eighth Annual Meeting of the Liberian Studies Association- Indiana University, Bloomington April 8-10 1976
Change within the Social and Political Structure of the Sikleo Kru by Thomas E. Hayden
Conference Schedule Eighth Annual Meeting of the Liberian Studies Association
Ethnicity and Trade: Hawkers and Petty Shopkeepers in Pandambu, Sierra Leone by Barry Issacs
Liberia and Sierra Leone: Alternative Patterns of Central-Local Linkage by Christopher Clapham
Liberian-Firestone Relations: Some Policy Implications for Economic and Social Development by James Teah Tarpeh
Loma Households and the Production of Rice: Implications for Commercial Production by Jeanette E. Carter
Patterning in Food Purchasing Activities and Preferences in Monrovia, 1970: an Oblique Factor Analysis by Vernon R. Dorjahn and Barry Issacs
Sabo Migrant Households by Frederick McEvoy
Survey of Psychological Research in Liberia by Orin James Martin
The Search for Matilda Newport by Jane Martin
Thomas Buchanan: Anti-Slavery Governor of Liberia, 1839-1841 by Dr. Rodney Carlisle
Unpublished Letter from Bassa Cove in 1847 from a Black American Missionary: Political and Medical Implications
Acquisition Information
donated by the family of Frederick Dean McEvoy
Copyright Transferred
Copyright interests for this collection have been transferred to the Trustees of Indiana University. For more information, contact the Indiana University Liberian Collections
Removed Materials
Below is a list or material that was removed from the Frederick McEvoy Collection. The material that was removed from the collection was either duplicates of material in the collection or was easily accessible in another format. The materials listed are arranged in alphabetical order by author.
Adams, Robert M. (1969)The Origins of Cities. Scientific American. W.H. Freeman and Company.
Almond, Gabriel A. (August, 1956) Comparative Political Systems. The Journal of Politics, Vol. 18
Atkins, John and Anthony F.C. Wallace. (February, 1960). The Meaning of Kinship Terms. American Anthropologist, Vol. 62
Careiro, Robert L. (September, 1956) Slash- and- Burn Agriculture: A Closer Look at its Implications for Settlement Patterns. Men and Cultures, Selected Papers of the Fifth International congress of Anthropological Ethnological Sciences. Anthony F.C. Wallace, ed.
Clark, Colin and Margaret Haswell. (1966). The Economics of Subsistence Agriculture. Primitive and Shifting Agriculture. London: Macmillian, NY: St. Martin's Press.
Dalton, George. (February, 1961) Economic Theory and Primitive Society. American Anthropologist, Vol. 63
Davis, Kingsley and Wilbert E. Moore. (April, 1945) Some Principles of Stratification. American Sociological Review, Vol. 10
De Grazia, Sebastian. (June, 1959) What Authority is Not. The American Political Science Review, Vol. LII
Duncan, Otis Dudley and Leo F. Schnore. (September, 1959) Cultural, Behavioral, and Ecological Perspectives in the Study of Social Organization. The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. LXV
Durkheim, Emile. (1947) Division of Labor in Society: Preface to the Second Edition Some Notes on Occupational Groups. The Division of Labor in Society, The Free Press.
Fallers, Llyod. (April, 1955) The Predicament of the Modern African Chief: An Instance from Uganda. American Anthropologist, Vol. 57
Fei, Hsiao-Tung. (July, 1946) Peasantry and Gentry: An Interpretation of Chinese Social Structure and its Changes. The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. LII
Foster, George M. (1953) What is Folk Culture? American Anthropologist, Vol. 55
Geertz, Clifford. The Impact of the Concept of Culture on the Concept of Man.
Gluckman, Max. (1949) Malinowski's 'Functional' Analysis of Social Change
Goody, Jack. (1972) The "Family" and the "Household." An Addison-Wesley Module in Anthropology. P 1-32.
Harris, David R. (1972) Swidden Systems and Settlement. A Warner Modular Publication. p 1-18.
Herskovits, Melville J. (1945) The Process of Cultural Change. The Science of Man in the World Crisis, Ralph Linton, (ed.)Columbia University Press
Jurgens, Hans W., Tracey, Kenneth A. and Peter K. Mitchell. Internal Migration in Liberia. Sierra Leone Geo. Association, No. 10.
Liebenow, J. Gus. (1969) Politics, Privilege and Progress in Liberia- a Review Article. Cornell University Press.
Linton, Ralph. (October, 1942) Age and Sex Categories. American Sociological Review, Vol. 7
Llyod, P.C. (July, 1960) Sacred Kingship and Government among the Yoruba. Africa, Vol. XXX, No. 3
McEvoy, Frederick Dean. (1977) Understanding Ethnic Realities Among the Grebo and Kru Peoples of West Africa.. Africa. p 62-79.
Merton, Robert K. (December, 1936) The Unanticipated Consequences of Purposive Social Action. American Sociological Review, Vol. 1
Netting, Robert McC. (1974) Agrarian Ecology. Annual Review of Anthropology. p 21-57.
Omer-Cooper, J.D. (1966) The Zulu Aftermath: A Nineteenth-Century Revolution in Bantu Africa (I Bantu South Africa before the Mfecane). Northwestern University Press. (3 copies)
Redfield, Robert. (January, 1947) The Folk Society. The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. LII
Rouse, Irving. (1939) Conceptual Technique. Prehistory in Haiti: a Study in Method. Yale University Publications in Anthropology, No. 21.
Sjoberg, Gideon. (November, 1952) Folk and "Feudal" Societies. The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. LVIII
Sjoberg, Gideon. (March, 1955) The Preindustrial City. The American Journal of Sociology, Vol. LX
Skinner, Elliott P. Labour Migration and Its Relationship to Socio-Cultural Change in Mossi Society
Smith, Philip E. L. (1972) Land-use, Settlement Patterns and Subsistence Agriculture: a Demographic Perspective. A Warner Modular Publication. p 1-17.
Southall, Aidan. (1974) State Formation in Africa. University of Wisconsin.
Steward, Julian H. (1936) The Economic and Social Basis of Primitive Bands. Essays in Anthropology in Honor of Alfred Louis Kroeber Berkeley:University of California Press
The Genealogical Method of Anthropological Inquiry. (1910) The Sociological Review, Vol. III.
Sabo (African people); Migrant Workers; Liberia; McEvoy, Frederick Dean; Firestone Plantations Company
- Publications and Manuscripts
  - McEvoy
    - Kinship Obligations and Entrepreneurship Conflicting or Supplementary, 1968
    - Migration from the Hinterland, 1968
    - Research on the Uses of Kinship in Sabo Labor Migration, 1968
    - The Significance of Labor Migration for Sabo Kinship, 1968
    - Some Problems in Sabo Kinships and Community Organization, 1969
    - Sabo Migrant Households, 1976
    - Slavery in Africa: Historical and Anthropological Perspectives, 1979
    - Ethnic Identification of Kru Speaking People, undated
    - History, Tradition, and Kinship as Factors in Modern Sabo Labor Migrants (abstract), undated
    - Levels of Ethnic Reality: Understanding 'Traditional' Politics in Southeastern Liberia, undated
  - Other
    - Wolpe, Howard E. Port Hardcourt: IBO Politics, 1968
    - Polgar, Steven.Culture and Family Planning, 1969
    - Holsoe, Svend. What Liberians Call Themselves and Each Other, 1970
    - Lalugba, Losay A. Tubman and Liberia: The Granduer and Potential Crisis of Charismatic Leadership, 1971
    - Understanding Ethnic Realities Among the Grebo and Kru of West Africa, 1973
    - Honnold, Edward. Firestone, 1975
    - Massing, Andreas. Ivory Coast's Development and its Impact on Liberia, 1975
    - Southwestern Association of Africanists, 1975
    - Wells, Louis T. Dr. Harley in Liberia, 1975
    - Carlisle, Rodney. Thomas Buchanan: Anti-Slavery Govenor of Liberia 1839-1842, 1976
    - Carlisle, Rodney and Martin, Jane. The Search for Matilda Newport, 1976
    - Carter, Jeanette E. Loma Households and the Production of Rice: Implications for Commercial Production, 1976
    - Clampham, Christopher. Liberia and Sierra Leone: Alternative Patterns of Central-Local Linkage, 1976
    - Dorjahn, Vernon R. and Issacs, Barry. Patterning in Food Purchasing Activities and Preferences in Monrovia 1970: an Oblique Factor Analysis, 1976
    - Eighth Annual Meeting Liberian Studies Association, 1976
    - Hayden, Thomas E. Change Within the Social and Poltical Structure of the Sikleo Kru, 1976
    - Issacs, Barry. Ethnicity and Trade: The Hawkers and Petty Shopkeepers in Pandembu, Sierra Leone, 1976
    - Martin, Orin James. Survey of Psychological Research in Liberia, 1976
    - Tarpeh, James Teah. Liberian-Firestone Relations: Some Policy Implications for Economic and Social Development, 1976
    - Unpublished Letter from Bassa Core in 1847 from a Black American Missionary: Political and Medical Significance, 1976
    - Dorjahn, Vernon R. The Present Setting for the Indigenous Economies of Sierra Leone and Libera, undated
    - Schmokel, Wolfe W. Liberia, Germans, Britian, and the United States 1905-1918, undated
    - Self Concepts of Elderly Liberian Settlers, undated
    - Service, Elman. History and Evolution: or Revolution Betrayed, undated
    - Sisay, Hassan. Black Loyalists in Search of the Promised Land, undated
    - Sundiata, I.K. The Dilemma: Afro-America and America-Liberia 1930-1934, undated
    - Weissange, Karin. The Mutual Realtionship Between Loma and Mandingo in Liberia According to Oral Tradition, undated
- Field Notes and Research Materials
  - Field Notes
    - Manuscripts and Field Notes, 1958-1967
    - Sabo Field Notes (Murdock System), 1966-1968
    - Sabo Field Notes (FPCO), 1966-1968
    - Sabo Field Notes, 1967
    - Field Note Journals, 1967-1968
  - Liberian Research Binders
    - Draft Research/ Notes on Literature/Some Field Notes, 1965-1966
    - Cavalla FPCO Plantation Census Forms/ Plantation Workers, 1966-1968
    - Census Forms/Genealogies/ Wufuke/Sweke/Sikuke/Jikeh, 1966-1968
    - Field Notes, 1966-1968
    - Rainfall/Weather, 1966-1968
    - Sabo Migrants/Plantation Notes and Analysis, 1966-1968
  - Research Materials
    - Various Charts, 1932-1969
    - Porter Notes and Reproduction, 1956
    - Sabo Migrant Workers, 1958-1968
    - Age-Grades/Age-Groups of Grebo and Kru, 1962-1967
    - Calculations, 1962-1967
    - Liberian Census, 1962
    - Ports of Trade, crica, 1963-1965
    - McEvoy- Thesis Draft, 1963-1967
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-1967
    - Archival Notes-Liberia, 1965-1967
    - Miscellaneous Notes from Published Sources, 1965-1967
    - Notes and Charts, 1965-1968
    - On West African Plantations, 1965
    - Background Historical Notes and Articles 1, 1966
    - Employment Histories Wufuke, 1966-1968
    - Kinship, 1966-1968
    - Migrant Organizations, 1966-1967
    - Slide and Negative Logs, 1966-1967
    - Archaeological Site Survey Form, 1967
    - Background Historical Notes and Articles 2, 1967-1975
    - Delafosse- Vocabulary, 1967
    - Genealogies, 1967
    - Household Census Forms w/ Maps and Write-ups, 1967
    - Inter-town Relations, 1967-1968
    - Language, 1967
    - Linguistics, 1967-1968
    - Maps: Drafts, crica, 1967
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1967
    - Sabo Kinship Terminology, circa, 1967-1968
    - Summary Notes, 1967
    - AAA "The Significance of Labor Migration for Sabo Kinship", 1968
    - Wage Labor, circa, 1968
    - Thesis Illustrations- Tracings, 1969
    - Map: Proof, 1978
    - Article Prep :Factors Effecting Labor Migration from Small Work Villages, undated
    - Charts; Genealogical Survey, undated
    - Classification of African Cultivated Plans by Type and Origin, undated
    - Miscellaneous Research Material, undated
    - Word Lists: Sabo and Tienpo, undated